Seriously, you two crossed a line
你们俩也太过分了吧
practicing behind our backs.
居然背着我们偷偷练习
What's the deal?
想干吗呀
Trying to steal my thunder
想故意抢走我
at the talent show?
才艺大赛的风头啊
But that song
不过刚才那首歌
was actually good.
还挺好听的
How about
要不然
we practice that song?
我们就练这首歌吧
Make a change again?
还改啊
Are you kidding?
咱都练了这么久了
We've been rehearsing for long!
还要改 有病吗
What's your opinion, then?
那还练不练了
Let's do it!
练呀
C'mon!
来
Our competitors seem strong, huh?
感觉对手都好强啊
Their outfits look great too.
他们的衣服也好好看呀
I think ours
我觉得我们的衣服
are nice too, right?
也很好看不是吗
We shouldn't let others shine while
千万不能长他人志气
we fade into the background.
灭自己威风 对不对
Where's Ling Dong?
胜呢
I don't know where he is.
对啊 他人呢
I haven't seen him around.
我没看到胜啊
Well, call him quickly.
不是 赶紧给胜打电话
I just tried calling him,
我刚刚已经打过了
but no answer.
但没人接
Everyone here now?
你们都来啦
Hi, Ms. Fang.
老师
How's the prep going?
准备得怎么样
Where's Ling Dong?
凌冬呢
He hasn't shown up yet.
他还没来
What?
没来
No worries,
没事 别着急
He won't drop the ball
凌冬肯定不是
when it counts.
关键时刻掉链子的人
Attention!
同学们
The competition is about to kick off.
比赛马上就要开始了
Get ready! Keep it up!
请各位做好准备 加油
What now?
怎么办
Stay calm.
没事 没事 别慌
Ma Yiming,
这样 马一鸣
go wait at the door.
你去门口等着
Bring Ling Dong straight here
一会儿凌冬过来了以后
when he arrives.
你直接带他过来
All right.
好
I'll go with you.
我陪你一块去
Let's go.
走
Esteemed leaders,
尊敬的各位领导
honored guests,
各位来宾
dear teachers, and fellow students,
亲爱的老师 同学们
good afternoon.
大家下午好
Welcome to the 13th
欢迎大家来到我市
Annual City High School Talent Show.
第十三届高中才艺大赛
On behalf of the organizers,
在此我谨代表主办方
I'd like to extend a warm welcome
对各位嘉宾的到来
and heartfelt thanks
表示热烈欢迎
to all of you.
和衷心感谢
I'm pleased to announce
现在我宣布
the official start
我市第十三届
of the Talent Show
高中才艺大赛
now!
正式开始
How did it go?
怎么样了
Waited at the door for half an hour,
在门口等了半小时
still no sign of him.
还没来
Chenjun High School, right?
辰郡中学是吗
You're next.
下一个到你们了
Get ready to wait in the wings.
准备去侧幕候场了
But our team isn't all here yet.
可是我们人还没齐呢
Can we
可不可以帮我们
go later, please?
安排后面一点啊
The order is fixed.
顺序都是定好的
If you want to switch,
如果想换的话
you need to negotiate with other teams.
只能跟后面的队伍协商
Okay. I'll go negotiate.
没事 这样 我去协商
You guys get ready.
你们好好准备
Xiangbei First High School, get ready.
湘北第一中学准备
♪Out the side of road shelter,♪
长亭外 古道边
♪grasses are green and wild.♪
芳草碧连天
It's quite a visual feast, isn't it?
真是一场视觉盛宴啊
Up next, I believe the performance
接下来这个节目呢
will take us into
将会带领我们进入
a different realm of art.
不一样的艺术殿堂
Now, please enjoy
下面请欣赏
the accordion solo
由俊德一中带来的
by Junde First High School,
手风琴独奏
"Lifting Your Spirits".
掀起你的盖头来
What do we do?
怎么办啊
Ms. Fang managed
方老师已经帮我们调到
to push us to last,
最后一个了
but...
但是
Let's improvise.
随机应变吧
Ling Dong?
凌冬
Why are you so late?
凌冬 你怎么才来啊
Sorry,
不好意思
got held up with something.
我有点事耽误了
Your face... What happened?
你 你 你脸怎么了
Let me get you a band-aid.
我去帮你拿创可贴
No need.
不用了
It's urgent.
时间紧任务重
Let's prepare first.
我们先准备一下吧
Jinghui, someone's watching us.
灰哥 有人看着呢
Let's perform first.
先演出
We'll settle scores later.
演出完之后跟你算账
Let's go!
走 上台
Thanks to Junde First High School
感谢俊德中学
for the brilliant performance.
带来精彩的节目演出
Youthful vigor, scholarly spirit,
恰同学少年 风华正茂
and commanding presence.
书生意气 挥斥方遒
Youth is a word
少年是一个光听
that just hearing it makes one
就让人觉得
feel clean and beautiful.
干净美好的词语
Next, please enjoy
下面请欣赏由辰郡中学
the band performance of Bright Time
带来的乐队演唱
by Chenjun High School.
未完成的时光
Please!
掌声有请
What's going on?
怎么回事啊
The lights went out.
灯灭了
It's our Chenjun High School's doing.
我们辰郡中学的
Until this moment,
直到这一刻
I truly believe for the first time
我第一次相信
that unstoppable passion and
无可阻挡的热血
determination for continuous improvement
和想要不断进步的决心
can eventually create miracles.
最终能创造出奇迹
Cheers!
干杯
Celebrating our rooftop squad's
庆祝我们天台小分队
successful performance!
演出成功
Congrats to Xiao Xiaohua
祝贺我们肖小画同学
for winning the Best Creativity Award
获得才艺大赛
at the Talent Show!
最佳创意奖
Xiao Xiaohua,
肖小画
you were amazing today!
你今天唱得太棒了
Not a single note was off.
一个音都没跑
All thanks to Lan Jinghui
这都是兰靖灰
for correcting my pitch so well.
纠正我音准纠正得好
These were just minor issues.
这都是小问题啊
We almost messed up today
只不过今天差点
because of someone.
就要被某人给搞砸了
I'm sorry,
对不起
I didn't mean to be late today.
我今天不是故意要迟到
Then why didn't you
那我打你电话
pick up my call?
你为什么不接
What happened?
这怎么搞的
Accidentally dropped it. It's fine.
不小心摔的 没事
Ling Dong definitely
凌冬肯定不是
didn't mean to be late.
故意迟到的
He must have been
他肯定是
delayed on the way.
路上有事耽搁了
Wait...
不是 不是
Stop talking about it.
你们快别说了
Let's eat before it gets cold.
赶紧吃饭 都凉了
But he...
那他
Lan Jinghui, have your food.
兰靖灰 你快吃吧
You deserve the most credit.
你功劳最大
He did a lot.
灰哥功劳大
I did my part too,
我功劳也不小啊
right?
是不是
Jinghui,
灰哥
you still haven't done
你之前答应我的事
what you promised me earlier.
我到现在都没见着
I've been busy
我这不是
teaching someone guitar
这些天教某人吉他
these days.
把这事给耽搁了吗
I promise,
我向你保证
I'll sort it out tomorrow.
明天就到位
This is delicious.
这好吃
Lan Jinghui,
兰靖灰
why do you do that gesture
你做那个手势
with your pinky on top?
小拇指怎么会在上面
Can't anyone do that?
这不是谁都可以吗
My pinky can only go below.
我的小拇指只能在下面
So can mine.
我也是
Wait...
不是 我
I can do it since I was little.
我打小就这么样了
Stop focusing on this weird detail.
行了 别关注这奇怪的点了
Let's eat.
赶紧吃饭吧
Enjoy it.
来来来
One more time.
再碰一次
Cheers!
干杯
The Best Creative Award
湘北市才艺比赛
of Xiangbei City Talent Show!
最佳创意奖
That's really amazing!
太厉害了 太厉害了
Baby, you've never
女儿啊 从小到大
won an award before,
你从来没得过奖
and now you've snagged
一得就得了
such a great one!
这么好的奖啊
Incredible!
牛死了
My daughter is on fire!
我女儿太厉害了
You've outdone your old man!
你超越老爸了
Where should we put it?
你说这个奖放哪儿
Where?
放哪儿
How about
放放放
the balcony?
放阳台吧
Yes, the balcony.
对对对 阳台 放阳台
No, no, it's not grand enough.
不不不 阳台太不隆重
It deserves something
不能放这里
How about
这样
the art room?
放到那个画室里面
Great,
对对对
But... it's not your award,
这 这又不是你得奖
why put it in the art room?
你放什么画室啊
Then...
这样 这样
how about...
放到
our daughter's bedroom?
放到女儿的这个卧室
That's cool!
对对对
No,
不行
it's a private room.
卧室她一个人看
The trophy should be placed
我们大家都看不到
somewhere everyone can see it.
我们要集体看
The dining room, okay?
饭厅 对不对
Fancy!
就饭厅
Morning. You're Xiao Xiaohua, right?
早啊 你就是肖小画吧
See you.
再见
Xiaohua, I really admire you.
小画 我好喜欢你的
Morning, Xiaohua.
早 小画
Keep it up, Xiaohua.
小画 加油
Xiaohua, keep it up.
小画 小画 加油 小画
Xiaohua, your video was awesome.
小画 你的视频真棒
Saw your video, Xiaohua.
小画 我看你了视频
Keep pushing, Xiaohua.
小画 你要加油啊
Xiaohua, you sang amazingly.
小画 你唱得真不错
Xiaohua.
小画
She's something else.
特别厉害
Xiaohua,
你真的特别特别厉害
Loved your video.
看了你的视频很喜欢你
Xiaohua.
小画
Qingtian,
晴天
it's so weird.
真的太奇怪了
When I walked into school,
我一进学校
tons of people I don't know
有好多不认识的人
greeted me,
跟我打招呼
totally freaked me out.
吓死我了
That's a good thing.
这是好事呀 小画
It means you're really popular now.
证明你现在很受欢迎
But I'm still not used to it.
可是我还不太习惯
No worries.
这 这有什么不习惯的
You just need time.
慢慢就习惯了
Xu Mengyu is over there.
徐梦予在那儿呢
No, I mean,
不是 不是
where's Xiao Xiaohua?
肖小画在哪儿
Xiao Xiaohua,
肖小画
someone's looking for you.
找你的
Your performance was stellar.
你们表演太精彩了
No... it's epic!
不 简直帅爆了
Here, take this.
这给你
Hope we can be friends.
希望能跟你成为朋友
Sure, thanks.
好 谢谢
Don't forget to read the letter.
记得看信啊
Xiaohua,
小画
you're practically a celebrity now,
你现在简直成了名人了
even have fans
都有支持者了
sending you letters.
给你送信呢
It's just a competition.
不就是参加个比赛吗
So what?
至于吗
What's the big deal?
有什么了不起的
Liu Shu,
刘姝
if you're jealous, just say it.
你忌妒小画就直说
Why beat around the bush?
干嘛呀这是
Jealous?
我忌妒她
Mengyu didn't make
去年我们梦予
such a big fuss
参加比赛的时候
when she competed last year, did she?
也没像她这么高调吧
Stop there.
行了
We need to go to the biology lab.
不去生物实验室了吗
What was that?
你干嘛
She was green with envy.
吃不着葡萄说葡萄酸
I've been waiting for you forever.
等你半天了
Lan Jinghui,
兰靖灰
not only are you
你现在不光是
the last in your grade,
年级最后一个到学校
but the last in the entire school.
全校你都是最后一个到
Winning that award get to your head?
昨天拿个奖膨胀了是吧
No way,
没有
how could I?
我怎么可能会膨胀
Serious now.
严肃点
Why were you late?
为什么迟到啊
Overslept.
睡过了
Seriously.
真就是睡过
Look at the dark shadows under my eyes.
你看我黑眼圈
Sleep-deprived?
缺觉
Go home and catch up on sleep.
回家接着睡去
Good morning, Mr. Zhang.
主任好
How come...
你怎么
you're late too?
你怎么也迟到了呀
Something wrong with my bicycle.
车坏了 早上刚修好
What happened to your face?
脸昨天摔的
Bumped into something. It's fine.
不小心弄的 没事
Get to class.
上课去吧
See you later.
主任再见
Ling Dong,
凌冬
be more careful riding your bike.
下次骑车小心点啊
Thank you. Bye.
知道了 主任 主任再见
Sir,
主任
you actually believe such a lame excuse?
这么扯的理由你都信
But what I just told you
我这是真的
is the truth...
我是真的睡
Why aren't you home yet?
你怎么还没回家呀
Get to class.
上课去
Now!
快点
All right,
走了 走了
thanks.
谢谢主任
Our main task
今天这节课呢
today
咱们主要任务是
is to work on these onions.
解决这些洋葱
The experiment topic
今天的实验主题
is crude extraction of DNA.
是基因的粗提取
Pair up freely
两两自由分组啊
with one for the experiment,
一个负责做实验
and the other for records.
另一个呢 负责记录
Onions can be quite irritating,
洋葱的刺激性比较大
so,
所以呢
you're provided with
每人桌上有一副护目镜
goggles and gloves.
还有一副手套
Clear so far?
大家都清楚了吗
Crystal clear.
清楚了
Sorry,
报告
teacher,
不好意思 老师
I'm late.
我迟到了
Be on time next time.
下次注意
Chenjun's Light reporting in.
辰郡之光前来报到
Lan Jinghui! Stop!
兰靖灰 你胡闹什么
Wanna be expelled?
不想上课了
No, no.
没有 没有
Go join Ling Dong's group.
去吧 和凌冬一组
Jinghui,
灰哥
where are my new shoes?
我的新鞋呢
Right on your seat.
在你位儿上
If you have any questions, just ask me.
有什么不懂的可以问我
Extracting and identifying DNA?
基因的粗提取与鉴定
Are we really doing such
我们现在这个阶段就能
advanced experiments at this stage?
做这么高级的实验吗
Is it in the textbook?
不 书上有吗这个
I've got it covered, no worries.
有我呢 怕什么
Just don't
你别到时候
end up not knowing
你又自己不会啊
what to do later.
撑不住
Too much...
多 多了
No, too little now.
又太少了
Mengyu,
梦予
the onions are all sliced for you.
你洋葱帮你切好了
Are you moved or something?
干啥呀 这么感动啊
C'mon, they're pungent!
谁感动 我是被你熏的
Quit staring and start recording.
别愣着 做记录
Come over here.
你过来一下
What for?
干嘛
I'm no good at this, don't rely on me.
我不会做 别依赖我啊
Help me take off my goggles.
帮我取下护目镜
I've got something on my hands.
我手上有东西
You're quite demanding, you know?
事怎么那么多呢
Put on.
戴上
Why?
为什么
I want my experiment notes
我希望我的实验记录
to be more precise,
可以更准确一些
okay?
可以吗
I can record accurately
我闭着眼睛
even with my eyes closed.
也能记录得很准确
Then keep writing:
那你继续记
filter the mixture
将混合液
through two layers of gauze,
用两层纱布滤出
then add the precipitated solution
然后将析出的溶液
to 10 milliliters pre-chilled
再加入十毫升的
ethanol solution,
预冷乙醇溶液
and let it sit.
然后静置
How'd you get that mark on your face?
你脸上伤怎么弄的
Note it down.
记
How are you handling this?
你们都怎么做的啊
Wow, Ling Dong,
天哪 不愧是凌冬
impressive speed
你看这速度
and accuracy.
这准确度
Ash Lan,
渣渣灰
you've lucked out with an ace teammate.
你摊上神队友了
You're practically coasting.
你简直躺赢
Coasting?
什么叫躺赢
I'm just as much a part of this team
我也是我们这个小组的
as anyone.
一份子好吗
No coasting
兢兢业业的
without
不记笔记
thorough notes,
哪儿来的这个躺赢
got it?
是不是
Are you done writing?
记完了吗
Get lost.
去
You guys distracted me and I forgot.
被你们这么一打岔忘了
Hurry up and leave.
快去 快去 快去
Why so grouchy? No fun at all.
凶什么凶嘛 真没劲
How about I handle the procedure
小画 要不然我来操作
and you do the recording?
你来记录吧
Okay.
好
Qingtian, it's torn.
晴天 破了
Each group only has one pair of gloves.
每个组只有一副手套哎
What now?
怎么办
Qingtian, take mine.
晴天 你用这个吧
Then what will you use?
那你用什么呀
Don't worry about me.
你别管了
Thank you.
谢谢你啊
She's my seatmate.
那是我同桌
What are you doing?
你要干啥
Just something a monitor should do.
这是我做班长该做的
Jinghui,
灰哥
where's my gift?
我的礼物呢
On your desk. Check it out yourself.
放你桌上了 自己看吧
An "A", a "J",
一个A 一个J
and a coconut for you.
还附送你个椰子
Jinghui!
灰哥
It's time for class!
要上课了
Lan Jinghui, Ma Yiming,
兰靖灰 马一鸣
what are you two doing?
你们俩干嘛呢
Jogging.
跑步呢
Get ready for class!
别跑步了 上课了
Class begins!
上课
Here.
还给你
Stand up.
起立
Hello, teacher.
老师好
Please take your seats.
同学们好 坐下吧
Everyone,
同学们
the mid-term exam
马上期中考试
is coming up soon.
就要开始了
I hope
我希望这一次
you'll take it seriously.
你们可以认真地对待
You start howling
我刚刚说完要考试
as soon as you hear it.
你们就开始嚎啊
Are you nervous?
你们也会紧张的吗
Yeah.
紧张
Some of you are usually
一个个上课迟到的
late for class, sleeping,
上课睡觉的
or not submitting homework.
还有一帮不交作业的
From what I see,
我看你们平时
you all seem quite relaxed.
挺轻松的啊
Ma'am,
老师
you've misunderstood.
那你可就误会了啊
We actually study hard in private.
我们私下可用功了
Am I right, Lan Jinghui?
是吧 兰靖灰
Yes.
是的
Are you serious?
认真吗
Yes, we are.
认真
Words are cheap.
口说无凭啊
We'll see the results.
我们成绩见分晓
Especially Ma Yiming
特别是你 马一鸣
and Lan Jinghui.
还有兰靖灰
I'll keep a close eye
你们俩是我
on both of you.
重点关注对象
Ma'am, I haven't done anything.
老师 我什么都没做 这
This is all a misunderstanding.
完全就是误伤啊
Misunderstanding or not,
误不误伤我不知道啊
when you two stop
什么时候你们两个
being at the bottom,
难兄难弟脱离了倒数
I'll shift my focus.
我就转移目标 好吧
Okay, let's start the class.
行 我们开始上课
Today, you'll learn
今天我们学习
about sequences.
数列的概念
What are you laughing at?
你笑什么呀
Let me tell you,
我告诉你啊
this kind of
就这种期中考试
mid-term exam
小小的考试
will be a pushover.
我根本就没有放在眼里
I'm not worried about you.
我不担心你
Conservatively speaking,
保守估计的话
without any surprise,
不出意外
you'll move up a hundred places.
前进一百名吧
You have that much confidence in me?
对我这么有信心啊
Nope,
不是对你有信心
it's confidence in myself.
是对我自己有信心
Ma Yiming, go play basketball with me.
走 马一鸣 打球
No.
不打
How about it?
怎么样
The coconut I gave you isn't bad, right?
哥送给你的椰子不错吧
Take it back. I don't want it.
还给你 我才不要
I have a question for you.
我问你个事
See any injury on Ling Dong's face?
你看到凌冬脸上伤没有
No, I didn't.
没有啊
Are your eyes
你的眼睛
just for show?
只是用来充数的吗
I'm... a man,
我 我一大老爷们
why would I stare at him all day?
整天盯着他看干嘛呀
Can't I look at my Mengyu instead?
我看我梦姐她不香吗
Besides,
还有
something's off about you.
你不对劲啊
Are you trying to mess with him again?
你是不是又想整他呀
I'm talking seriously here.
我跟你说正经的呢
Maybe he bumped into something himself.
那他可能就是自己撞的
Doesn't seem like it.
不像
If so,
如果他是撞的
there would be bruises.
那这儿一定会有淤青
He scratched himself with his own nails.
那他自己指甲划的
Not possible.
不可能
He doesn't have nails.
他一大老爷们都没指甲
How could he scratch himself?
拿什么划呀
Jinghui, I really don't know.
灰哥 我真不知道
I'm not a forensic doctor.
我又不是法医
Why are you telling me these?
你跟我说这些
The most crucial point is...
最关键的一点
he was late this morning.
他今天早上迟到了
Have you ever seen such a thing happen?
你见过他迟到吗
No.
没有
Now that you mention it,
你这么一说
something does seem off.
是有点不对劲
Right!
是吧
Did he get into trouble outside
他是不是在外边惹事
and someone beat him up?
让人给砸了
I mean, got beaten up.
揍 不是砸
Was he beaten up?
被人揍了
That was a good performance.
弹得真好
Thanks.
谢谢啊
Does my son's composition sound good?
我儿子编那曲子好听吗
Ling Dong also participated in.
二表舅好像也编了
But most of it was done by my son.
主要还是我儿子编的
He learned guitar
他那吉他
from my son.
都是我儿子教的
Alright. You're impressive,
行行行 你厉害
and the best in the world.
行吧 你全世界第一
You just wanna hear me say
小灰有你当年的风范
that like a father, like a son, right?
你不就想听这句话吗
He doesn't quite match up
这小子比起当年的我
to me back in the day.
还是差点意思
Does he know
小灰现在知道
our relationship now?
咱们俩什么关系了吗
Don't tell him, though.
别告诉他啊
Otherwise, he'll be rebellious
要不然在学校里边
at school.
不服管
I think he's just
我觉得呢
rebelling against you.
他是不服你管
Ling Dong manages him quite well.
他二表舅管得挺好的
He is my cousin!
那是我二表弟啊
He's definitely great!
能差了吗
Let me tell you something serious.
我跟你说点正事啊
Over these years,
你这些年呢
I've tried to support
托我给凌冬他们家
Ling Dong's family,
所有的资助
but his mom refused all of it.
嫂子呢 全部拒绝了
I think,
我想着是呢
after her husband
很有可能是
passed away,
老凌走了以后呢
she couldn't get over it.
嫂子心里这坎没过去
You understand?
你明白我意思吧
All right, one step at a time.
行啊 慢慢来吧
How about another song?
怎么着 再来一首
Let's do it.
走啊
Let's go.
走着